Register of the Andrzej Pomian papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Andrzej Pomian papers
1937-1973
2009C45
Hoover Institution Archives
21 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder, 7 motion picture film reels (8.8 linear feet)
The collection includes materials related to Poland, the Polish Underground, the Warsaw Uprising, Polish politics and government during and after World War II and Polish émigré affairs, in the form of correspondence, writings, reports, publications, notes, and clippings. Also available on microfilm (36 reels).
Pomian, Andrzej
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (36 reels).
Related Materials
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych records, Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji records, Hoover Institution Archives
Wolnosc i Niezawislosc miscellaneous records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Andrzej Pomian, who died in Washington, D.C., in 2008 at the age of ninety-seven, was a Polish émigré journalist and author who worked for many years for Radio Free Europe. During World War II, he was a ranking officer in the Information and Propaganda Bureau of Poland's clandestine Home Army, the largest underground organization in Nazi-occupied Europe. Extracted from Poland in April 1944 in one of the most spectacular air operations of the war, Pomian spent the next ten years with the Polish government in exile in London before moving to the United States.
Andrzej Pomian, the name he assumed during the war, was born Bohdan Salacinski in 1911 in a Polish village in Podolia, the part of western Ukraine absorbed by the Soviet Union in 1920. Escaping the Soviets, the family moved to Warsaw, where Bohdan was educated, receiving his law degree from the University of Warsaw in 1932 and remaining at the university as an assistant professor. From the beginning of the German occupation, Pomian was involved in underground work. He taught law in an underground university and worked in various units of the resistance, eventually becoming a director of the Information and Propaganda Bureau, which coordinated the underground intelligence and publication work of the Home Army and controlled underground radio programming, as well as photographic and film documentation units. The Bureau's "Action N" section published documents in German aimed at weakening the morale of the German army and colonists in Poland. In general, the Home Army was involved in sabotage, self-defense, and retaliation activities against the Germans. It also provided key service to the Allies in the area of intelligence, monitoring troop movements in the east, and the development of German secret V-1 and V-2 rockets. The primary purpose of the Home Army, however, was to prepare for the anticipated German military collapse and the liberation of the country. After the Allied landing in Italy and the westward advance of the Red Army, a great national uprising, focused in Warsaw, was planned for the second half of 1944.
In connection with this plan, the Home Army and underground civilian authorities delegated several officers, including Pomian, to report to the Polish and British authorities in London on the progress of the preparations. Such contacts were usually carried out by coded radio transmissions or solitary couriers or emissaries. There were regular night flights from England or southern Italy to drop supplies and people into occupied Poland. A new joint Polish-Special Operations Executive operation, Wildhorn I, including actual landing and return flight, was undertaken in the evening of April 15, 1944. A Douglas Dakota, unarmed but equipped with eight additional fuel tanks, left its base near Brindisi in southern Italy. It flew over the Balkans and the Carpathian Mountains into Poland, to a stubble field near the city of Lublin, southeast of Warsaw. The field was marked out by bonfires and secured by several forest companies of the Home Army. Agents and bags of U.S. dollars were unloaded, and Pomian and his colleagues boarded the Dakota, barely avoiding the intense and bloody firefight that erupted between the Home Army units and the pursuing Wehrmacht columns. The return flight via Brindisi and Gibraltar brought Pomian to England twenty-four hours later.
Pomian followed the tragic epilogue of the war in Poland from distant London. During his ten years there, Pomian continued working for the Polish government in exile, coordinating contacts and organizing financial support for the anticommunist underground and Home Army veterans. He moved to the U.S. in 1955.
Biographical Chronology
1911 January 2 Born, Bohdan Salacinski in Czarny Ostrów, in present-day Ukraine
1920 Evacuates to Poland with his family after the Polish-Russian War
1930s Studies law at Warsaw University and works in the municipal solicitor general's office
1940s Practices law and lectures in an underground university after the German occupation of Poland. He also works in the Central Command of the Polish Home Army in the Information and Propaganda Bureau
1944 April Evacuates from Poland by airplane during Operation Wildhorn I as an emissary to the Polish government-in-exile in London
1944-1954 Works on the staff of the commander-in-chief of the Polish government-in-exile as leading liaison operations with the Polish underground
1946 Author, Warsaw Rising
1949 Author, Stalin and the Poles
1950 Author, Polish Armed Forces in World War Two: The Home Army
1955 Emigrates to the United States
1956-1977 Works as the Washington correspondent for the Polish section of Radio Free Europe
1974-1977 Completes a three-year assignment in Munich
1977 Returns to Washington and retires
1977-2000s Freelances for radio and publishes articles on history, politics, and literature in the Polish Daily (London) and Polish Daily News (New York)
1990 Author, Poland Defends Her Independence 1918-1945
1991 Receives the Warsaw University Medal
2000 Awarded the Commander's Cross with Star by the president of Poland and receives the Joseph Conrad Literary Award from the Jozef Pilsudski Institute of New York
2008 April 20 Dies, Washington D.C.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes materials related to the Polish underground during and after World War II, with particular emphasis on the Warsaw Uprising of 1944 and the Soviet occupation of Poland, and Polish émigré affairs, in the form of reports, publications, correspondence, clippings, writings, and notes. The collection encompasses the years 1937-1973, with the bulk of the materials covering 1944-1954.
The bulk of the material relates generally to Andrzej Pomian's work as the assistant director of the Information and Propaganda Bureau of the Home Army in occupied Poland (1941-1944) and his role as the chief liaison between the Polish underground and the government-in-exile (1944-1954).
Some correspondence, and some Home Army and government-in-exile material can be found interspersed with post-war notes, clippings, and publications in the subject file.
Stowarzyszenie Polskich Kombatantów.; Polish people--United States.
- Biographical file, 1944-1954
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, personal documents, and receipts. Arranged by physical form.
  - Family correspondence, 1944-1954 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Personal documents, correspondence, 1944-1952 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Receipts, notes, correspondence, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1944-1954.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Anders, Wladyslaw, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Gierat, Ewa and Stanislaw, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Grubinski, Waclaw, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Kukiel, Marian, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Sujkowski, Zbigniew, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Talarek-Gronowski, Roman, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Terlecki, Tymon, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Tyszkiewicz, Samuel and Wiktoria, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Wegorek, Zygmunt, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Wolodko, Norbert, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Wyczalkowski, Marian, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Zalewski, August, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Zenczykowski, Tadeusz "Kania," 1944-1946 (Box-folder 1: 16)
- Home Army and government-in-exile file, 1941-1954.
  Reports, notes, correspondence, publications and financial records related to the Home Army and Andrzej Pomian's role as liaison between the government-in-exile and the postwar Polish underground. Arranged chronologically.
  - "Akcja N," 1941-1945. Anti-Nazi German-language propaganda (Box-folder 1: 17, Map case)
  - Biuro Informacji I Propagandy Krajowych Sil Zbrojnych, BIPKSZ, circa 1943 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Publications, 1943-1944. (Box-folder 1: 19-20)
    Contains photos, leaflets, Insurekcja, Biuletyn Informacyjny, Polska Ilustrowana, Sprawy Polskie, Kobieta w Walce, Przeglad Polityczny, Nowe Drogi, Wiadomosci Polskie
  - Home Army and "Akcja N,", 1943-1948. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Reports, correspondence, notes
  - Polish underground and postwar publications, 1943-1952. (Box-folder 2: 2)
    Includes photostat copies,
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 3-4)
    Photographs of underground publications
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    News digests, anecdotes
  - Warsaw Uprising, August 1944. (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
    Press digests and orders
  - Poland, Ministry of the Interior, Social Division, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Reports from the Warsaw Uprising
  - Poland, Ministry of the Interior, Social Division, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 5-10)
    Review of the national press during the Warsaw Uprising, parts 1-6
  - Photos, reports on the situation in Poland and the Yalta Conference, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Situational reports on Soviet-occupied Poland from the Ministry of Information and Documentation and the Ministry of the Interior, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944-1946. (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Reports, press digests, correspondence
  - Digests of messages received from Poland, in English; correspondence/publications relating to Polish government-in-exile propaganda and information distribution, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Home Army, 1944-1950. (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Reports, pamphlets
  - Typescript chronology of the Warsaw Uprising, circa 1945 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Narodowe Sily Zbrojne N.S.Z., 1945-1946. (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Reports, underground publications
  - Polish Government budget documents, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Correspondence, party platforms, meeting minutes, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Notes, receipts, pamphlets, correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - "WIN", 1946-1947. (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Plan of operations, correspondence, receipts, brochures relating to émigré affairs
  - Polish underground, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    Publications, photos
  - Polish government-in-exile, 1946-1950. (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Financial records and film
  - Polish underground, 1946-1954. (Box-folder 6: 2)
    Correspondence, instructions, reports, receipts, leaflets
  - Financial records, receipts, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Polish underground group "Farys" and its cooperation with British intelligence, 1951-1954. (Box-folder 6: 4)
    Correspondence, reports
- Writings, 1945-1960.
  Typescripts, manuscripts of books and other writings, and transcripts of Pomian's Radio Free Europe broadcasts. Arranged chronologically.
  - Operation Tempest "Burza" and the Warsaw Uprising, undated. (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Manuscript, notes
  - "Niepodleglosc I Demokracja," freedom movement, undated. (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Typescript, manuscript and notes
  - The Soviet Union and the Home Army, undated. (Box-folder 7: 2)
    Typescript and manuscript
  - Typescripts, reports, clippings, undated (Box-folder 7: 3-4)
  - Powstanie Warszawskie, 1946 (Box-folder 7: 5-7)
    Typescript
  - Polish underground, 1947 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    Manuscripts and typescripts
  - Anthology of the Warsaw Uprising, 1954 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
    Sheet music, lyrics, poetry
  - Radio Free Europe, 1954 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    Correspondence, transcripts, notes
  - Tradycje Demokracji Polskiej, 1954 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    Manuscripts, typescript
  - Z Dziejow Polski Podziemnej, 1955-1956. (Box-folder 8: 5)
    Transcripts
  - Z Dziejow Polski Podziemnej, 1959 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Radio Free Europe, 1960 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
- Subject file, 1939, 1944-1958.
  Clippings, publications and notes. Arranged alphabetically.
  - General
    - Booklet/letter, 1946, 1955 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Clippings, notes, reports, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Clippings, 1944-1953 (Box-folder 9: 6-7)
    - Clippings, 1944-1953 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
    - Clippings, periodicals, typescripts, notes, 1944-1955 (Box-folder 10: 3-6)
    - Clippings, newspapers, 1955 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Clippings, photos, letters, notes, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Clippings, notes, scripts, correspondence, pamphlets, 1944-1958 (Box-folder 11: 3-8)
    - Clippings, 1945-1955 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Clippings, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Notes, orders, clippings, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - Notes, clippings, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Notes, songs, poems, reminiscences, 1954 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Notes, clippings, pamphlets, 1944-1952, 1955, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - Notes, clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, 1944-1954 (Box-folder 13: 1-5)
    - Notes, publications, and periodicals, 1941-1950 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
    - Pamphlets, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - Party platforms, bulletins, photos of Stanislaw Mikolajczyk, 1947 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - Publications, 1944-1955. (Box-folder 14: 5)
      Includes Robotnik, Robotnik Polski, Tygodnik Warszawski, Gazeta Ludowa, Polska Zbrojna, Dzis I Jutro, Polska Walczaca, Jutro Polski, Biuletyn Informacyjny, Zycie, Dziennik Polski I Dziennik Zolnierza, Glos, Tygodnik Powszechny
    - Reports, pamphlets, periodicals, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - Reports, periodicals, prayer cards, notes, 1945-1954 (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - Typescript screenplay, undated (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Typescript personal narratives, undated (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Typescripts, 1945, 1947 (Box-folder 15: 3)
      Includes Powstanie Warszawskie by Antoni Chrusciel "Monter"
    - Typescripts, notes, publications, correspondence, 1946 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - émigré affairs, 1945-1953. (Box-folder 16: 1)
    Serials, clippings, report
  - Home Army, undated. (Box-folder 16: 2)
    Bibliography of underground publications, notes and typescript
  - Home Army and political organizations, undated. (Box-folder 16: 3)
    Notes, typescripts, clippings
  - Polish underground, undated. (Box-folder 16: 4-5)
    Songs, poems
  - Polish underground, 1943, 1946, 1948-1949. (Box-folder 16: 6)
    Typescript, correspondence
  - Soviet occupation of Poland during and after World War II, 1946-1948. (Box-folder 16: 7)
    Typescripts
  - Warsaw Uprising, undated. (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
    Typescript, poetry
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1954 (Box-folder 17: 3)
    Notes, clippings
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944 (Box-folder 17: 4-5)
    Typescript, notes, digest of messages
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944, 1954. (Box-folder 18: 1)
    Notes, clippings, typescripts, reports
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944 (Box-folder 18: 2)
    Clippings, photographs,
  - Warsaw Uprising 10th anniversary, 1954 (Box-folder 18: 3)
    Clippings, articles, correspondence
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1947 (Box-folder 19: 1)
    Clippings, notes, poems
  - Warsaw Uprising and Polish émigré affairs, 1947 (Box-folder 19: 2)
    Clippings, publications, newsletters, bibliography
  - Warsaw Uprising, 1944-1951. (Box-folder 19: 3-5)
    Clippings, photos, correspondence, bibliographies
  - "WIN,", 1952-1953. (Box-folder 19: 6)
    Pamphlets, clippings
  - Wodewil Warszawski, by Edward Chudzynski, 1954 (Box-folder 19: 7)
    Script for a play
  - World War II, 1939-1947. (Box-folder 19: 8)
    Clippings, correspondence, September 1, 1939 newspaper
- Stowarzyszenie Polskich Kombatantów file, 1969-1973.
  Correspondence, financial records, and printed matter, relating to activities of the Polish-American veterans' organization Stowarzyszenie Polskich Kombatantów and Polish émigré affairs. Arranged chronologically.
  - Baczynski, K.K., 1972 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Brezhnev, L.I., 1973 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - Ciehanowski, Gladys, 1973 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - Cives Leopolienses, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 20: 4)
  - Galinski, Adam, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 20: 5)
  - Hemar, Marian, 1972 (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - Karski, Jan, 1973 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Katyn, 1972 (Box-folder 20: 8)
    Printed matter
  - Lot, 1973 (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - Ostrowski, Tadeusz, 1972 (Box-folder 20: 10)
  - Paczkowski, Jerzy, 1971 (Box-folder 20: 11)
  - Polish-American Congress, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 20: 12)
  - Project Pole, 1972 (Box-folder 20: 13)
  - SPK combatants, 1972-1973. (Box-folder 20: 14)
    General
  - SPK correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 20: 15-17)
  - SPK members, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 20: 18)
  - SPK combatants printed matter, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - SPK combatants printed matter "Kombatant...,", 1971-1972 (Box-folder 21: 2)
  - Reports, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 21: 3)
  - Statute, 1953 (Box-folder 21: 4)
  - Troscianko, Wiktor, 1973 (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Veteran's Bill, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 21: 6)
  - Warsaw Ghetto Anniversary, 1973 (Box-folder 21: 7)
- Sound Recordings, 1956-1964
  Contains 4 reels and 1 phonorecord, relating to Jan Paderewski, the Warsaw Uprising, Communism in Poland, and the U.S. presidential election of 1956.
  - T. Machrowicz New Year's Address, undated, Warsaw Uprising Tribute broadcast on Belgian Radio (French), 1/4 inch reel, August, 1964 (Box 21)
  - "Poland Under Communism," Interview with Andrzej Pomian, 1/4 inch reel, June 21, 1963 (Box 21)
  - Flannery on Paderewski, 1/4 inch reel, undated (Box 21)
  - "Ballads for Ballots" sung by Joe Glazer, phonorecord, 1956 (Box 21)
- Maps, 1937-1948 (Box 22, Map case)
  Poland, Germany, and progress of the Warsaw Uprising
- Motion Picture Films (Film shelf shelf)
  Titles taken directly from the film reels.
  - "Polish Bombers Holiday," 35mm film print, black & white, sound, 1000 ft., circa 1943
    Opening credits read: Polish Air Force Film Unit Presents, Polish Bombers Holiday.
    Access
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 2009C45_f_0010675.
  - "WWII Polish Army en route from USSR via Africa-Italy-France to Germany - Polish Version," 35mm film print, black & white, sound, 1000ft.
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 2009C45_0011243_r01
  - "Polish Bombers Holiday," duplicate 35mm film print
  - "Sport Kajakowy w Polsce," 35mm film print
  - "WWII Polish Paratroopers Porizade 2nd Part Polish Version," 35mm film print
  - "Najkrotsza Droga," 35mm film print
  - "A Vol D'oiseau," 35mm film print